<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diella certaine sonnets, adioyned to the amorous poeme of Dom Diego and Gineura. By R.L. Gentleman.</title>
            <author>Linche, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845396</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845396</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06630)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 554:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Diella certaine sonnets, adioyned to the amorous poeme of Dom Diego and Gineura. By R.L. Gentleman.</title>
                  <author>Linche, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by James Roberts] for Henry Olney, and are to be sold at his shop in Fleetstreete, neer the Middle-temple gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.L. = Richard Linche.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-F.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Diella,</hi> Certaine Sonnets, adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the amorous Poeme of <hi>Dom Diego</hi> and <hi>Gineura.</hi> (⸪)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By R. L. Gentleman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ben balla, á chi fortuna ſuona.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed for <hi>Henry Olney,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Fleetſtreete, neer the Middle-temple gate. 1596.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST worthily honoured, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous beautified Lady, the Ladie <hi>Anne Glemnham,</hi> wife to the moſt noble, magnanimious, and woorthy Knight, Sir <hi>Henry Glemnham. &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, your many honourable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, hauing tyed mee to your eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſeruice, to ſhevve ſome part of my dutie, I preſent your Ladiſhip with a fewe paſsionate Sonnets, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled
<pb facs="tcp:10293:3"/>
vvith the loues of <hi>Dom Diego</hi> and <hi>Gineura.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Daine (gentle Lady) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them, and therein ſhew the greatneſſe of your benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, in receiuing curteouſlie a gift of ſo ſmal worth, which though it cannot any wayes equall eyther the number of your vertues, or the greatnes of that noble houſe, whence your Ladiſhip is diſcended, impute it not (Madam) to my defect of iudgement, but of Fortune, for were I furniſhed with the greateſt riches that
<pb facs="tcp:10293:3"/>
blind Goddeſſe could beſtow on a man of my ſtate, both they, and I woulde fall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at your feete, and euer reſt at your Ladiſhips deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yet Madam as it is, it is a chylde of the Muſes, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worthy to be cherriſhed, conceiued in the braine of a gallant Gentleman, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be fauoured: ſent into the worlde by mee, who haue euer honoured your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp, and therefore craue of your Ladiſhip to bee protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:10293:4"/>
to whom I euer vviſhe long life, lengthened with all honorable happines.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips in all dutie, <hi>Henry Olney.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:4"/>
            <head>Sonnet. I.</head>
            <l>WHen firſt the feather'd God did ſtrike my hart,</l>
            <l>with fatall and ymedicable wound,</l>
            <l>Leauing behind the head of his fell dart,</l>
            <l>my bloodleſſe body fell vnto the ground;</l>
            <l>And, when with ſhame I reinforc'd my might,</l>
            <l>boldly to gaze on her ſo heauenly face,</l>
            <l>Huge flames of fire ſhe darted from her light,</l>
            <l>which ſince haue ſcorcht me in moſt pitious caſe,</l>
            <l>To quench which heate, an Ocean of teares</l>
            <l>haue guſhed out from forth my red-ſwolne eyes,</l>
            <l>But deep-fetch'd ſighes this raging flame vpreares,</l>
            <l>and blowes the ſparkes vp to the purple skies.</l>
            <l>Whereat, the Gods afraid that heauen ſhould burne,</l>
            <l>Intreated <hi>Loue</hi> that I for e're might mourne.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:5"/>
            <head>Sonnet II.</head>
            <l>SOone as the Azur-color'd Gates of th'Eaſt,</l>
            <l>were ſet wide open by the watchful Morne,</l>
            <l>I walkt abroad, (as hauing tooke no reſt)</l>
            <l>(for nights are tedious to a man forlorne,)</l>
            <l>And viewing well each pearle-bedewed flower,</l>
            <l>then waxing dry by ſplendour of the ſunne,</l>
            <l>All ſcarled-hew'd I ſaw him gin to lower,</l>
            <l>and bluſh, as though ſome haynous act were don.</l>
            <l>At this amaz'd, I hy'de me home amaine,</l>
            <l>thinking that I his anger cauſed had;</l>
            <l>And at his ſet, abroad I walkt againe,</l>
            <l>when (loe) the Moone lookt wondrous pale and ſad.</l>
            <l>Anger the one, and enuie mou'd the other,</l>
            <l>To ſee my loue more faire then Loues faire mother.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:5"/>
            <head>Sonnet III.</head>
            <l>SWift-footed Time, looke back &amp; here mark well</l>
            <l>thoſe rare-ſhapt parts my pen ſhal now declare</l>
            <l>My miſtres ſnow-white skinne doth much excell</l>
            <l>the pure-ſoft woll Arcadyan ſheepe doe beare;</l>
            <l>Her hayre exceedes gold forc'd in ſmalleſt wyre,</l>
            <l>in ſmaller threds then thoſe <hi>Arachne</hi> ſpun;</l>
            <l>Her eyes are chriſtall fountaines, yet dart fire,</l>
            <l>more glorious to behold then Mid-day ſun;</l>
            <l>Her Iuory front, (though ſoft as pureſt ſilke)</l>
            <l>lookes like the table of Olympick <hi>Ioue,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Her cheekes are like ripe cherries layd in milke,</l>
            <l>her Alablaſter neck the throne of Loue;</l>
            <l>Her other parts ſo farre excell the reſt,</l>
            <l>That wanting words, they cannot be expreſt.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:6"/>
            <head>Sonnet IIII.</head>
            <l>WHat ſugred termes, what all-perſwading arte,</l>
            <l>what ſweet mellifluous words, what wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding lookes</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Loue</hi> vſd for his admittance to my hart?</l>
            <l>ſuch eloquence was neuer read in bookes;</l>
            <l>He promiſd pleaſure, reſt, and endleſſe ioy,</l>
            <l>fruition of the faireſt ſhee aliue,</l>
            <l>His pleaſure paine, reſt trouble, ioy annoy,</l>
            <l>haue I ſince found, which me of bliſſe depriue;</l>
            <l>The Troian horſe thus haue I now let in,</l>
            <l>wherein incloſd theſe armed men were plac'd,</l>
            <l>Bright eyes, faire cheekes, ſweet lips, &amp; milk-white skin</l>
            <l>theſe foes my life haue ouerthrown &amp; raz'd.</l>
            <l>Faire outward ſhewes, proue inwardly the worſt,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Loue</hi> looketh faire, but Louers are accurſt.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:6"/>
            <head>Sonnet V.</head>
            <l>THE little Archer viewing well my loue,</l>
            <l>ſtone-ſtill amaz'd, admired ſuch a ſight,</l>
            <l>And ſwore he knew none ſuch to dwell aboue,</l>
            <l>though many faire, none ſo conſpicuous bright:</l>
            <l>With that inrag'd, (flamigerous as he is)</l>
            <l>he now gan loathe his <hi>Pſiches</hi> louely face,</l>
            <l>And ſwore great other to rob me of my bliſſe,</l>
            <l>ſaying that earth for her was too too baſe;</l>
            <l>But <hi>Cytherea</hi> checkt her lordly ſonne,</l>
            <l>commaunding him to bring no giglet thether,</l>
            <l>Fearing indeed, her amorous ſports were done</l>
            <l>with hote-ſpur <hi>Mars,</hi> if hee ſhould once but ſee her.</l>
            <l>If then her beauty moue the Gods aboue,</l>
            <l>Let all men iudge if I haue cauſe to loue.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:7"/>
            <head>Sonnet VI.</head>
            <l>MIrror of beautie, Natures faireſt chyld,</l>
            <l>Empreſſe of loue, my harts high-prized Iewell,</l>
            <l>Learne of the Doue, to loue and to be milde,</l>
            <l>be not to him that honors thee ſo cruell,</l>
            <l>But as the Aſpe, deafe, angry, nothing meeke,</l>
            <l>thou wilt not liſten to my dolefull plaint,</l>
            <l>Nor once wilt looke on my diſcolored cheeke,</l>
            <l>which wanting blood, cauſeth me oft to faint;</l>
            <l>Then ſilent will I be, if that will pleaſe thee,</l>
            <l>yet ſo, as in my ſtead, each Plaine, each Hill,</l>
            <l>Shall eccho forth my griefe, and thereby caſe mee,</l>
            <l>for I my ſelfe of ſpeaking haue my fill;</l>
            <l>If Plaines, and Hills, be ſilent in my paine,</l>
            <l>My death ſhall ſpeake, and tell what I ſuſtaine.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:7"/>
            <head>Sonnet VII.</head>
            <l>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Loue had firſt beſieg'd my harts ſtrong wal,</l>
            <l>rampaird and countermur'd with chaſtitie,</l>
            <l>And had with Ordnance made his tops to fall,</l>
            <l>ſtouping their glory to his ſurquedry,</l>
            <l>I call'd a parley, and withall did craue</l>
            <l>ſome compoſition, or ſome friendly peace;</l>
            <l>To this requeſt, he his conſent ſoone gaue,</l>
            <l>as ſeeming glad ſuch cruell warrs ſhould ceaſe,</l>
            <l>I, (nought miſtruſting) opened all the gates,</l>
            <l>yea, lodg'd him in the Pallace of my hart,</l>
            <l>VVhen (loe) in dead of night he ſeekes his mates,</l>
            <l>and ſhewes each Traytor how to play his part;</l>
            <l>VVith that they fir'de my hart, and thence gan flie,</l>
            <l>Their names, Sweet ſmiles, Faire face, &amp; piercing Eye</l>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:8"/>
            <head>Sonnet VIII.</head>
            <l>LIke to a Faulcon watching for a flight,</l>
            <l>duly attending his deſired game,</l>
            <l>Haue I oft watcht and markt to haue a ſight,</l>
            <l>of thy faire face exceeding niggard Fame,</l>
            <l>Thyne eyes (thoſe Semynaries of my griefe)</l>
            <l>haue been more gladſome to my tyred ſpright,</l>
            <l>Then naked ſauadges receiue reliefe,</l>
            <l>by comfort-bringing warmth of <hi>Phoebus</hi> light;</l>
            <l>But when each part ſo glorious I had ſeene,</l>
            <l>I trembled more then Autumnes parched leaues,</l>
            <l>Mine eyes were greedy whirlepooles ſucking in</l>
            <l>that heauenly faire which me of reſt bereaues;</l>
            <l>Then as thy beauty thus hath conquerd mee,</l>
            <l>(Faire) let relenting pitty conquer thee.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:8"/>
            <head>Sonnet IX.</head>
            <l>BLot not thy beautie (faireſt) yet vnkinde,</l>
            <l>with cruell vſage of a yeelding hart,</l>
            <l>The ſtouteſt Captaine ſcornes ſuch bloody minde,</l>
            <l>then mingle mercy where thou cauſedſt ſmart;</l>
            <l>Let him not die in his May-ſpringing dayes,</l>
            <l>that liuing vowes to honour thee for euer,</l>
            <l>Shine forth ſome pitty from thy ſun-like rayes,</l>
            <l>that hard froz'd hate may ſo diſſolue and ſeuer;</l>
            <l>Oh, were thou not much harder then a flint,</l>
            <l>thou had'ſt ere this been melted into loue,</l>
            <l>In firmeſt ſtone ſmall raine doth make a print,</l>
            <l>but ſeas of teares cannot thy hardnes moue.</l>
            <l>Then wretched I muſt die before my time,</l>
            <l>Blaſted &amp; ſpoyled in my budding prime.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:9"/>
            <head>Sonnet X.</head>
            <l>WHen <hi>Flora</hi> vaunts her in her proude array,</l>
            <l>clothing faire <hi>Tellus</hi> in a ſpangled gowne,</l>
            <l>VVhen <hi>Boreas</hi> furie is exild away,</l>
            <l>and all the VVelkin cleer'd from cloudy frowne,</l>
            <l>At that ſame time all Natures chyldren ioy,</l>
            <l>trees leaues, flowers bud, plants ſpring, &amp; beaſts increaſe,</l>
            <l>Only my ſoule, ſurcharg'd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deep annoy,</l>
            <l>cannot reioyce, nor ſighes nor teares can ceaſe:</l>
            <l>Onely the grafts of ſorrow ſeeme to grow,</l>
            <l>ſet in my hart, no other ſpring I finde,</l>
            <l>Delights and pleaſures are o're growne with woe,</l>
            <l>laments and ſobs poſſeſſe my weeping minde;</l>
            <l>The froſt of griefe ſo nyps Delight at roote,</l>
            <l>No ſunne but ſhee can doe it any boote.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:9"/>
            <head>Sonnet XI.</head>
            <l>WHat ſhee can be ſo cruell as my Loue,</l>
            <l>or beare a hart ſo pittileſſe as ſhee?</l>
            <l>VVho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue, lookes, words, teares, prayers doe not moue,</l>
            <l>nor ſighes, nor vowes preuaile to pittie mee.</l>
            <l>Shee calls my loue a <hi>Synon</hi> to her hart,</l>
            <l>my lookes (ſhee ſaith) are like the Crocadyles,</l>
            <l>My words the Syrens ſing with guilefull arte,</l>
            <l>teares, <hi>Cyrces</hi> flouds, ſighes, vowes, deceitful guiles,</l>
            <l>But my poore hart hath no interpreter,</l>
            <l>but loue, lookes, words, teares, prayers, ſighes or vowes,</l>
            <l>Then muſt it die, ſith ſhee my Comforter,</l>
            <l>what ere I doe, nor liketh, nor allowes.</l>
            <l>VVith <hi>Titius,</hi> thus the vultur Sorrow eats me,</l>
            <l>With ſteele-twig'd rods thus tyrant <hi>Cupid</hi> beats me.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:10"/>
            <head>Sonnet XII.</head>
            <l>THou, (like the faire-fac'd gold-encouerd booke,</l>
            <l>whoſe lines are ſtuft with damned hereſies)</l>
            <l>Doſt in thy face beare a celeſtial looke,</l>
            <l>when in thy hart liue hell-borne cruelties.</l>
            <l>With poyſenous Toades y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cleereſt ſpring's infected</l>
            <l>and pureſt Launes nought worth if ful of ſtaines,</l>
            <l>So is faire beauty when true loue's reiected;</l>
            <l>when cole-blacke hate within the hart remaines,</l>
            <l>Then loue, (my deere) let that be Methrydate</l>
            <l>to ouer-come the venome of diſdaine;</l>
            <l>Be pittifull, tread downe this killing hate,</l>
            <l>conuert to ſugred pleaſure, gall-full paine.</l>
            <l>O, ſith Diſdaine is foe vnto thy Faire,</l>
            <l>Exile him thence, there let him not repaire.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:10"/>
            <head>Sonnet XIII.</head>
            <l>I Know, within my mouth for baſhfull feare,</l>
            <l>and dread of your diſdaine, my words wil die;</l>
            <l>I know, I ſhall be ſtriken dumbe (my deere)</l>
            <l>with doubt of your vnpittifull reply;</l>
            <l>I know, when as I ſhall before you lie</l>
            <l>proſtrate and humble, crauing help of you,</l>
            <l>Miſtie aſpects will cloude your ſun-bright eye,</l>
            <l>&amp; ſcornefull lookes oreſhade your beauties hewe,</l>
            <l>I know, when I ſhall pleade my loue ſo true,</l>
            <l>ſo ſtaineleſſe, conſtant, loyall, and vpright,</l>
            <l>My truthfull pleadings will not cauſe you rue</l>
            <l>the ne're-heard ſtate of my diſtreſſed plight.</l>
            <l>I know, when I ſhall come with face bedight</l>
            <l>with ſtreaming teares, faln fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my fountaine eyes,</l>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:11"/>
            <head>Sonnet XIII.</head>
            <l>Breathing forth ſighes of moſt hart-breaking might,</l>
            <l>my teares, my ſighes, and me, you will deſpiſe,</l>
            <l>I know, when with the power that in me lyes,</l>
            <l>and all the prayers and vowes that women moue,</l>
            <l>I ſhall in humbleſt mercy-mouing wiſe</l>
            <l>intreate, beſeech, deſire, and beg your loue,</l>
            <l>I know, (ſweet mayden) all will not remoue</l>
            <l>flynt-harted rigour from your rocky breaſt,</l>
            <l>But all my meanes, my ſute, and what I proue,</l>
            <l>proues bad, and I muſt liue in all vnreſt.</l>
            <l>Dying in life, and liuing ſtill in death,</l>
            <l>And yet nor die, nor drawe a life-like breath.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:11"/>
            <head>Sonnet XIIII.</head>
            <l>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> broad-fac'd riuers turne vnto their fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains</l>
            <l>and hungry Wolues deuoured are by Sheep,</l>
            <l>When Marine Dolphins play on ſnow-tipt Mountains</l>
            <l>&amp; foule-form'd Beares do in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ocean keep,</l>
            <l>Then ſhall I leaue to loue, and ceaſe to burne</l>
            <l>in theſe hot flames wherein I now delight,</l>
            <l>But this I knowe, the Riuers ne're returne,</l>
            <l>nor ſilly Sheep with rauening Wolues dare fight,</l>
            <l>Nor Dolphins leaue the Seas, nor Beares the woods,</l>
            <l>for Nature bids them all to keepe their kind,</l>
            <l>Then eyes, rayne forth your ouer-ſwelled floods,</l>
            <l>till drowned in ſuch Seas may make you blind:</l>
            <l>Then (harts delight) ſith I muſt loue thee euer,</l>
            <l>Loue me againe, and let thy loue perſeuer.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:12"/>
            <head>Sonnet XV.</head>
            <l>NO ſooner leaues <hi>Hyperion Thetis</hi> bed,</l>
            <l>and mounts his coach to poſt from thence away,</l>
            <l>Richly adorning faire <hi>Lencotheas</hi> head,</l>
            <l>gyuing to mountaynes tincture from his ray:</l>
            <l>But ſtraight I riſe, where I could find no reſt,</l>
            <l>where viſions and fantaſies appeare,</l>
            <l>And when with ſmall adoo my body's dreſt;</l>
            <l>abroad I walke to thinke vpon my deere;</l>
            <l>VVhere vnder vmbrage of ſome aged Tree,</l>
            <l>with Lute in hand I ſit and (ſighing) ſay,</l>
            <l>Sweete Groues tell forth with Eccho what you ſee:</l>
            <l>good Trees beare witnes who is my decay,</l>
            <l>And thou my ſoule, ſpeake, ſpeake, what reſt I haue,</l>
            <l>When each our ioyes diſpayre doth make me raue.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:12"/>
            <head>Sonnet XVI.</head>
            <l>BVt thou my deere ſweet-ſounding Lute be ſtill,</l>
            <l>repoſe thy troubled ſtrings vpon this moſſe,</l>
            <l>Thou haſt full often eaſd me gainſt my will,</l>
            <l>lye down in peace, thy ſpoile were my great loſſe,</l>
            <l>Ile ſpeake inough of her (too cruell) hart,</l>
            <l>enough to mooue the ſtonie Rocks to ruth,</l>
            <l>And cauſe theſe trees weepe tears to heare my ſmart</l>
            <l>though (cruell ſhe) will not once way my truth,</l>
            <l>Her face is of the pureſt white and red,</l>
            <l>her eyes are chriſtall, and her haire is gold,</l>
            <l>The world for ſhape with garlands crown her head,</l>
            <l>And yet a Tygreſſe hart dwells in this mold:</l>
            <l>But I muſt loue her (Tigreſſe) too too much,</l>
            <l>Forc'd muſt I loue, becauſe I finde none ſuch.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:13"/>
            <head>Sonnet XVII.</head>
            <l>THE ſun-ſcorcht Sea-man when he ſees the Seas</l>
            <l>all in a furie hoiſe him to the skye,</l>
            <l>And throwe him down againe (as waues do pleaſe)</l>
            <l>(ſo chaſed clouds from <hi>Eols</hi> maſtiues flye)</l>
            <l>In ſuch diſtreſſe prouideth with great ſpeede</l>
            <l>all meanes to ſaue him from the tempeſts rage,</l>
            <l>Hee ſhewes his wit in ſuch lyke time of neede,</l>
            <l>the big-ſwolne billowes furie to aſſwage;</l>
            <l>But fooliſh I, although I ſee my death,</l>
            <l>and feele her proud diſdayne too feelinglie,</l>
            <l>VVhich me of all felicitie bereaueth,</l>
            <l>yet ſeeke no meanes t'eſcape this miſerie:</l>
            <l>So am I charm'd with hart-inchaunting beautie,</l>
            <l>That ſtill to waile I thinke it is my dutie.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:13"/>
            <head>Sonnet XVIII.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>CVpid</hi> had done ſome heynous act or other,</l>
            <l>that caus'd <hi>Idalea</hi> whip him very ſore;</l>
            <l>The ſtubborne Boy away runs from his Mother,</l>
            <l>proteſting ſtoutly to returne no more;</l>
            <l>By chance I met him, who deſir'd reliefe,</l>
            <l>and crau'd that I ſome lodging would him giue,</l>
            <l>Pittying his lookes which ſeemed drown'd in griefe,</l>
            <l>I tooke him home there thinking hee ſhould liue,</l>
            <l>But ſee the Boy; enuying at my lyfe,</l>
            <l>which neuer ſorrowe, neuer loue had taſted,</l>
            <l>Hee rays'd within my hart ſuch vncouth ſtryfe,</l>
            <l>that with the ſame my body now is waſted:</l>
            <l>By thankleſſe Loue, thus vilely am I vſed,</l>
            <l>By vſing kindnes, I am thus abuſed.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:14"/>
            <head>Sonnet XIX.</head>
            <l>WHen night returnes backe to his vgly mantion,</l>
            <l>&amp; cleer-fac'd morning makes her bright vpriſe,</l>
            <l>In ſorowes depth, I murmur out his caution,</l>
            <l>(ſalt teares diſtilling from my dewy eyes)</l>
            <l>O thou deceitfull <hi>Somnus</hi> God of Dreames,</l>
            <l>ceaſe to afflict my ouer-pained ſpright</l>
            <l>VVith vayne illuſions, and idle Theames,</l>
            <l>thy ſpells are falſe, thou canſt not charme aright,</l>
            <l>For when in bed I thinke t'imbrace my loue,</l>
            <l>(inchaunted by thy magique ſo to thinke)</l>
            <l>Vaine are my thoughts, tis empty ayre I proue,</l>
            <l>that ſtill I waile, till watching make me winke:</l>
            <l>And when I winke I wiſh I nere might wake,</l>
            <l>But ſleeping carryed to the <hi>Stigian</hi> Lake.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:14"/>
            <head>Sonnet XX.</head>
            <l>THE ſtrongeſt Pyne that Queene <hi>Feronia</hi> hath,</l>
            <l>growing within her woody Emperie,</l>
            <l>Is ſoone throwne downe by <hi>Boreas</hi> windy wrath,</l>
            <l>if one roote onely his ſupporter be,</l>
            <l>The talleſt Ship that cuts the angry Waue,</l>
            <l>and plowes the Seas of <hi>Saturnes</hi> ſecond ſunne;</l>
            <l>If but one Anchor for a iourney haue,</l>
            <l>when that is loſt gainſt euery Rocke doth runne;</l>
            <l>I am that Pyne (faire loue) that Ship am I,</l>
            <l>and thou that Anchor art and roote to me,</l>
            <l>If then thou faile, (oh faile not) I muſt die,</l>
            <l>and pyne away in endleſſe miſerie:</l>
            <l>But words preuaile not, nor can ſighes deuiſe,</l>
            <l>To mooue thy hart, if bent to tyrannize.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:15"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXI.</head>
            <l>AS winters rage young plants vnkindly ſpilleth,</l>
            <l>as haile greene Corne, and lightning floures periſh,</l>
            <l>So mans decay, is loue, whoſe hart it killeth,</l>
            <l>if in his ſoule bee carefully it cherriſh;</l>
            <l>O how alluringly hee offers grace,,</l>
            <l>and breathes newe hope of lyfe into our thought,</l>
            <l>VVith cheerefull, pleaſant, (yet deceitfull) face</l>
            <l>he creepes, &amp; fawnes, till in his net w'are caught,</l>
            <l>Then, when he ſees vs Captiues by him led,</l>
            <l>and ſees vs proſtrate humbly crauing helpe,</l>
            <l>So feirce a Lyon <hi>Lybia</hi> neuer bred,</l>
            <l>nor Adders ſting, nor any Tigreſſe whelpe:</l>
            <l>Oh bleſt be they that neuer felt his force,</l>
            <l>Loue hath nor pittie, mercy, nor remorſe.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:15"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXII.</head>
            <l>LOoke as a Bird, through ſweetnes of the call</l>
            <l>doth cleane forget the fowlers guilefull trap;</l>
            <l>Or one that gazing on the ſtarres doth fall</l>
            <l>in ſome deepe pit bewayling his miſhap;</l>
            <l>So wretched I, whilſt with <hi>Lynceus</hi> eyes,</l>
            <l>I greedily beheld her Angels face,</l>
            <l>VVas ſtraight intangled with ſuch ſubtilties,</l>
            <l>as euer ſince I liue in wofull caſe;</l>
            <l>Her cheekes were Roſes, layd in chriſtall glaſſe,</l>
            <l>her breaſtes two aples of <hi>Heſperides,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Her voyce more ſweete then famous <hi>Thamiras,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>reuiuing death with dorique mellodies:</l>
            <l>I harkning ſo to this attractiue call,</l>
            <l>VVas caught, and euer ſince haue liu'd in thrall.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:16"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXIII.</head>
            <l>MY lyues preſeruer, hope of my harts bliſſe,</l>
            <l>when ſhall I know the doome of life or death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Hells fearefull torments eaſier are then this</l>
            <l>ſoules agonie, wherein I now doe breath,</l>
            <l>If thou would'ſt looke, this my teare-ſtayned face,</l>
            <l>dreery, and wan, far diffring from it was,</l>
            <l>VVould well reueale my moſt tormentfull caſe</l>
            <l>and ſhewe thy faire, my griefe as in a glaſſe:</l>
            <l>Looke as a Deere late wounded very ſore,</l>
            <l>among the Heard full heauely dooth feede,</l>
            <l>So do I lyue: expecting euermore,</l>
            <l>when as my wounded hart ſhold ceaſe to bleede:</l>
            <l>How patient then would I endure the ſmart,</l>
            <l>Of pitchy-countnanc'd Deaths dead-doing dart.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:16"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXIIII.</head>
            <l>WHen leaden-harted ſleepe had ſhut mine eyes,</l>
            <l>and cloſe o'redrawn their windolets of light,</l>
            <l>Whoſe watrynes the fire of griefe ſo dries,</l>
            <l>that weep they could no longer, ſleep they might,</l>
            <l>Mee thought, I ſunke downe to a poole of griefe,</l>
            <l>and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (me thought) ſuch ſinking much did pleaſe me</l>
            <l>But when I downe was plung'd paſt all reliefe,</l>
            <l>with flood-fill'd mouth I call'd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome wold eaſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </l>
            <l>Whereat (me thought) I ſaw my deereſt loue,</l>
            <l>(fearing my drowning) reach her hand to mine,</l>
            <l>VVho pull'd ſo hard to get me vp aboue,</l>
            <l>that with the pull ſleepe did forſake mine eyne:</l>
            <l>But when awakt I ſawe t'was but a dreame,</l>
            <l>I wiſht t'had ſlept and perriſht in that ſtreame,</l>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:17"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXV.</head>
            <l>ROugh ſtormes haue calmes, lopt boughes do grow againe,</l>
            <l>the naked winter is recloth'd by ſpring,</l>
            <l>No yeare ſo drie, but there doth fall ſome raine,</l>
            <l>Nature is kind (ſaue me) to euery thing,</l>
            <l>Onely my griefes do neuer end nor ceaſe,</l>
            <l>no ebbe doth followe my ſtill-flowing teares,</l>
            <l>My ſighes, are ſtormes which neuer can appeaſe</l>
            <l>their furious blaſtes procur'd by endleſſe cares,</l>
            <l>Then ſighes and ſobs, tell <hi>Tantalus</hi> he's bleſt,</l>
            <l>goe flye to <hi>Titius</hi> tell him hee hath pleaſure,</l>
            <l>So tell <hi>Ixion</hi> though his wheele ne're reſt,</l>
            <l>their paines are ſports impoſed with ſome meaſure</l>
            <l>Bid them be patient, bid them looke on me,</l>
            <l>And they ſhall ſee the Map of miſerie.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:17"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXVI.</head>
            <l>THE loue-hurt hart which Tyrant <hi>Cupid</hi> wounds,</l>
            <l>proudly inſulting o're his conquer'd pray,</l>
            <l>Doth bleede a freſh where pleaſure moſt abounds,</l>
            <l>for mirth and mourning alwayes make a fray.</l>
            <l>Looke as a Bird ſore bruzed with a blowe,</l>
            <l>(lately deuiding notes moſt ſweetly ſinging)</l>
            <l>To heare her fellowes how in tunes they flowe,</l>
            <l>doth droope &amp; pine, as though her knel were ringing,</l>
            <l>The heauie-thoughted Prys'ner full of doubt,</l>
            <l>dolefully ſitting in a cloſe-bar'd cage,</l>
            <l>Is halfe contented, till hee looketh out,</l>
            <l>he ſees each free, then ſtormes hee in a rage;</l>
            <l>The ſight of pleaſure trebleth euery payne,</l>
            <l>As ſmall Brooks ſwell and are inrag'd with rayne.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:18"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXVII.</head>
            <l>THE heauens Herrald may not make compare</l>
            <l>of working words which ſo abound in thee,</l>
            <l>Thy hony-dewed tongue exceedes his far,</l>
            <l>in ſweete diſcourſe, and tunefull mellodie,</l>
            <l>Th'amber-color'd treſſe which <hi>Berenice</hi>
            </l>
            <l>for her true-louing <hi>Ptholomeus</hi> vow'd,</l>
            <l>VVithin <hi>Idaleas</hi> ſacred Aphrodice,</l>
            <l>is worth-leſſe with thy lockes to be allow'd,</l>
            <l>To thee my thoughts are conſecrate (deere loue)</l>
            <l>my words &amp; phraſes bound to pleaſe thine eares,</l>
            <l>My lookes are ſuch as any hart could moue,</l>
            <l>I ſtill ſollicit thee with ſighes and teares:</l>
            <l>O let not hate eclypſe thy beauties ſhine,</l>
            <l>Then none would deeme thee earthly, but deuine.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:18"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXVIII</head>
            <l>WEarie with ſeruing where I nought could get,</l>
            <l>I thought to croſſe great <hi>Neptunes</hi> greateſt Seas,</l>
            <l>To lyue in exile; but my drift was let,</l>
            <l>by cruell Fortune ſpightfull of ſuch eaſe,</l>
            <l>The Ship I had to paſſe in, was my minde,</l>
            <l>greedie deſire was topſaile of the ſame,</l>
            <l>My teares were ſurges, ſighes did ſerue for winde,</l>
            <l>of all my Ship diſpayre, was cheifeſt frame,</l>
            <l>Sorrowe was Maiſter, care the cable rope,</l>
            <l>griefe was the maine Maſt, Loue the Captaine of it,</l>
            <l>He that did rule the helme, was fooliſh hope,</l>
            <l>but beautie was the Rocke that my ſhip ſplit:</l>
            <l>Which ſince hath made ſuch ſhipwrack of my ioy,</l>
            <l>That ſtill I ſwim in th'Ocean of annoy.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:19"/>
            <head>Sonnet. XXIX.</head>
            <l>CEaſe eyes to cherriſh with ſtil-flowing teares</l>
            <l>the almoſt witherd rootes of dying griefe,</l>
            <l>Dry vp your running Brooks, &amp; dam your meares,</l>
            <l>and let my body die for moiſt reliefe,</l>
            <l>But death is deaffe, for well he knowes my paine,</l>
            <l>my ſlakeleſſe payne hells horror doth exceede,</l>
            <l>There is no hell ſo blacke as her diſdaine</l>
            <l>whence cares, ſighes, ſorrowes, and all griefes do breed,</l>
            <l>In ſteede of ſleep, (when day incloiſtred is</l>
            <l>in duſtie pryſon of infernall Night)</l>
            <l>With broad-wakt eyes I waile my miſeries,</l>
            <l>and if I winke, I feare ſome vgly ſight;</l>
            <l>Such fearefull dreames do haunt my troubled mind,</l>
            <l>My Loue's the cauſe, cauſe ſhee is ſo vnkind.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:19"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXX.</head>
            <l>HEe that can count the candles of the skie,</l>
            <l>reckon the Sands whereon <hi>Pactolus</hi> flowes,</l>
            <l>Or number nomberleſſe ſmall Attomie,</l>
            <l>what ſtrange, &amp; hideous monſters <hi>Nilus</hi> ſhowes,</l>
            <l>What miſhapt Beaſts vaſt <hi>Affrica</hi> doth yield,</l>
            <l>what rare-form'd fiſhes lyue in th' Ocean,</l>
            <l>What colour'd flowers doe grow in <hi>Tempes</hi> field,</l>
            <l>how many houres are ſince the world began,</l>
            <l>Let him, none elſe, gyue iudgement of my griefe,</l>
            <l>let him declare the beauties of my Loue,</l>
            <l>And hee will ſay my paines paſſe all reliefe,</l>
            <l>and hee will iudge her for a Saint aboue;</l>
            <l>But as thoſe things ther's no man can vnfolde,</l>
            <l>So, nor her faire, nor my griefe may be tolde.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="33" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:20"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXXIII.</head>
            <l>THinking to cloſe my ouer-watched eyes,</l>
            <l>and ſtop the ſluce of their vnceſſant flowing,</l>
            <l>I layd me downe when each one gan to riſe,</l>
            <l>(new-riſen <hi>Sol</hi> his flame like cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t'nance ſhewing)</l>
            <l>But griefe, though drowſie euer, yet neuer ſleepes,</l>
            <l>but ſtill admits freſh entercourſe of thought,</l>
            <l>Duly the paſſage of each houre he keepes,</l>
            <l>nor would he ſuffer me with ſleepe be caught,</l>
            <l>Some broken ſlumbers <hi>Morpheus</hi> had lent,</l>
            <l>who greatly pittied my want of reſt,</l>
            <l>Whereat my hart a thouſand thanks him ſent,</l>
            <l>and vow'd to ſerue him he was ready preſt;</l>
            <l>Let reſtleſſe nights, daies, howres, doe their ſpight,</l>
            <l>Ile loue her ſtill, and loue for me ſhall fight.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="34" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:20"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXXIIII.</head>
            <l>WHY ſhould a Maydens hart be of that proofe,</l>
            <l>as to reſiſt the ſharpe-point'd darte of loue?</l>
            <l>My Miſtres eye kills ſtrongeſt man aloofe,</l>
            <l>mee thinks he's weak that cannot quaile a Doue.</l>
            <l>A louely Doue, ſo faire and ſo diuine,</l>
            <l>able to make what <hi>Cynick</hi> ſo e're liueth,</l>
            <l>Vpon his knees to beg of her bright eyne</l>
            <l>one ſmiling looke, which life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death reuiueth.</l>
            <l>The frozen hart of cold <hi>Zenocrates,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>had beene diſſolued into hote deſire,</l>
            <l>Had <hi>Phryne</hi> caſt ſuch ſun-beames from her eyes,</l>
            <l>(ſuch eyes are cauſe that my hart flames in fire.)</l>
            <l>And yet with patience I muſt take my woe,</l>
            <l>In that my deereſt loue will haue it ſo.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="35" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:21"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXXV.</head>
            <l>ENd thys enchauntment (Loue) of my deſires,</l>
            <l>let me no longer languiſh for thy loue,</l>
            <l>Ioy not to ſee mee thus conſume in fires,</l>
            <l>but let my cruell paines thy hard hart moue,</l>
            <l>And now at laſt, with pittifull regard,</l>
            <l>eye me thy Louer, lorne for lack of thee,</l>
            <l>VVhich dying, liues in hope of ſweet reward,</l>
            <l>which hate hath hetherto with-held from me,</l>
            <l>Conſtant haue I been, ſtill in fancie faſt,</l>
            <l>ordayn'd by heauens to dote vpon thy faire,</l>
            <l>Nor will I e're, ſo long as life ſhall laſt,</l>
            <l>ſay any's fairer, breathing vitall ayre;</l>
            <l>But when the Ocean ſands ſhall lye vnwet,</l>
            <l>Then ſhal my ſoule to loue thee (Deere) forget.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="36" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:21"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXXVI.</head>
            <l>LOng did I wiſh before I could attaine</l>
            <l>the lookt for ſight I ſo deſir'd to ſee,</l>
            <l>Too ſoone at laſt I ſaw what bred my baine,</l>
            <l>and euer ſince hath ſore tormented mee;</l>
            <l>I ſawe her ſelfe, whom had I neuer ſeene,</l>
            <l>my wealth of bliſſe had not been turn'd to baile,</l>
            <l>Greedy regard of her, my harts ſole Queene,</l>
            <l>hath chang'd my ſommers ſun, to winters haile.</l>
            <l>How oft haue I, ſince that firſt fatall howre,</l>
            <l>beheld her all-faire ſhape with begging eye,</l>
            <l>Till ſhee (vnkind) hath kild me with a lowre,</l>
            <l>and bad my humble-ſuing lookes, looke by.</l>
            <l>O pitty mee (faire Loue) and higheſt fame</l>
            <l>Shall blazed be in honour of thy name.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="37" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:22"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXXVII.</head>
            <l>DID I not loue her as a Louer ought,</l>
            <l>with pureſt zeale, and faithfulnes of hart,</l>
            <l>Then ſhee had cauſe to ſet my loue at nought,</l>
            <l>and I had well deſeru'd to feele this ſmart,</l>
            <l>But holding her ſo deerely as I doe,</l>
            <l>as a rare Iewell of moſt high eſteeme,</l>
            <l>Shee moſt vnkindly wounds and kills me, ſo</l>
            <l>my nere-ſtain'd troth moſt cauſeles to miſdeeme,</l>
            <l>Neuer did one account of woman more,</l>
            <l>then I of her, nor euer woman yet,</l>
            <l>Reſpected leſſe, or held in leſſer ſtore</l>
            <l>her Louers vowes, then ſhee by mine doth ſet.</l>
            <l>VVhat reſteth then, but I diſpaire and die,</l>
            <l>That ſo my death may glut her ruthleſſe eye.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="38" type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:22"/>
            <head>Sonnet XXXVIII.</head>
            <l>HArken awhile <hi>(Diella)</hi> to a ſtorie,</l>
            <l>that tells of beauty, loue, and great diſdaine,</l>
            <l>The laſt, cauſd by ſuſpect; but ſhee was ſorry</l>
            <l>that tooke that cauſe, true loue ſo much to paine,</l>
            <l>For when ſhe knew his faith to be vnfained,</l>
            <l>ſpotles, ſincere, moſt true, and pure vnto her,</l>
            <l>Shee ioy'd as if a kingdome ſhee had gained,</l>
            <l>and lou'd him now as when he firſt did woo her.</l>
            <l>I nere incurd ſuſpition of my truth,</l>
            <l>(faireſt <hi>Diella</hi>) why wilt thou be cruell?</l>
            <l>Impoſe ſome end to vndeſerued ruth,</l>
            <l>and learne by others how to quench hates fuell.</l>
            <l>Reade all, my Deere, but chiefly marke the end,</l>
            <l>And be to mee, as ſhee to him, a friend.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:23"/>
            <head>THE LOVE OF DOM <hi>Diego</hi> and <hi>Gyneura.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IN <hi>Catheloygne,</hi> o'repeerd by <hi>Pyren</hi> Mountaines,</l>
               <l>(a Prouince ſeated in the Eaſt of Spaine,</l>
               <l>Famous for hunting ſports &amp; cleereſt fountains)</l>
               <l>a young heroyck gallant did remaine;</l>
               <l>Hee, Signior <hi>Dom Diego</hi> had to name,</l>
               <l>Who for his conſtant faith had got ſuch fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nature had tryde her deepeſt skill on him,</l>
               <l>(for ſo the heauen-borne powers had her deſired)</l>
               <l>With ſuch perfection framed ſhee each lim,</l>
               <l>that at her owne worke ſhee herſelfe admired,</l>
               <l>Maieſtick <hi>Ioue</hi> gaue him a Princely grace,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> wit, and <hi>Venus</hi> gaue his face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This loue-ſome youth, kinde Natures faireſt child,</l>
               <l>what for his beautious loue-alluring face,</l>
               <l>And for he was ſo gracious and ſo milde,</l>
               <l>was deem'd of all to be of heauenly race;</l>
               <l>Men honord him, and Maydens gaue him loue,</l>
               <l>To make him famous Men and Maydens ſtroue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:24"/>
               <l>Hunting he lou'd, nor did he ſcorne to loue,</l>
               <l>(a truer-louing hart was neuer knowne)</l>
               <l>Which well his Miſtres cruelly did proue,</l>
               <l>whoſe cauſeleſſe rigor Fame abroad hath blowne.</l>
               <l>But now lets tell, how hee on hunting went,</l>
               <l>And in what ſports ſuch pleaſant time he ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soone as the ſunne had left his watry bed,</l>
               <l>(bluſhing for ſhame that he ſo long had ſlept)</l>
               <l>Reuiuing thoſe which duskie Night made dead,</l>
               <l>when for his welcom Lambes on mountains lept.</l>
               <l>Vp ſtarts <hi>Diego,</hi> and with ſhrill-voyc'd horne,</l>
               <l>Tells hounds &amp; huntſmen of a cleere-fac'd morne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cloth'd all in Greene, (<hi>Syluanus</hi> lyuery)</l>
               <l>he wore a low-crown'd hat of fineſt ſilke,</l>
               <l>Whoſe brim turnd vp, was faſtned with a Ruby,</l>
               <l>and vnderneath, a Pearle as white as milke,</l>
               <l>A ſleeueles coate of Damaske, richly laced</l>
               <l>With Indian pearle, as thicke as could be placed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A gliſtring Cutlax pendent by his ſide,</l>
               <l>(he much eſteem'd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beaſt-diſmembring blade)</l>
               <l>And halfe-leg'd Buskins curiouſly ytide</l>
               <l>with loopes of burniſht gold full finely made,</l>
               <l>Thus goes <hi>Diego,</hi> chiefeſt of his name,</l>
               <l>With ſiluer-headed ſpeare to finde ſome game.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:24"/>
               <l>Long while it was ere any ſport began,</l>
               <l>at laſt a Hart his big-growne hornes did ſhew,</l>
               <l>VVhich (winding ſtraight the huntſmen) gan to run</l>
               <l>as faſt as arrow from a Parthyan bow:</l>
               <l>In whoſe purfute (by wil of powreful Fates)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diego</hi> loſt himſelfe, and all his mates.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Left thus alone in midſt of vnknowne place,</l>
               <l>he inuocates the fauourable ayde</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Ariadne,</hi> who with ſmaleſt lace,</l>
               <l>freed Monſter-killing <hi>Theſeus,</hi> ſo diſmaid,</l>
               <l>In worſer Laborinth did he now remaine,</l>
               <l>For none ſaue trees or beaſts, could heare him plain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In theſe Meanders, ſtragling heere and there,</l>
               <l>goes faire <hi>Diego,</hi> liſtning to each ſound,</l>
               <l>Muſing twixt purple hope, and paliſh feare,</l>
               <l>he thought to reſt him (wearied) on the ground,</l>
               <l>But ſee, he heares a farre ſome forced noyſe,</l>
               <l>A horne, a hound, or els ſome human voyce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVith that, Deſire, which ſcornes leaſt tedious let,</l>
               <l>directed him vnto that very place,</l>
               <l>Where loe to hunt the tymerous Hare, were met</l>
               <l>as Knights, ſo Ladies, fitteſt for that chaſe:</l>
               <l>Mongſt which, there came a Grace of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly faire,</l>
               <l>Her name <hi>Gyneura,</hi> with the golden hayre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:25"/>
               <l>Her hayre of ſuch corruſcant glitterous ſhine,</l>
               <l>as are the ſmalleſt ſtreames of hotteſt ſunne,</l>
               <l>Like ſtarres in froſtie night, ſo looke her eyne,</l>
               <l>within whoſe Arches Chriſtall ſprings doe run,</l>
               <l>Her cheekes faire ſhow of pureſt Porphyrie,</l>
               <l>Full curiouſly were typt with roſcall die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her lips like ripened Cherries ſeem'd to be,</l>
               <l>from out whoſe concaue Corrall—ſeeming Fount,</l>
               <l>Came ſweeter breath then muske of Araby,</l>
               <l>whoſe teeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> white of blanched pearle ſurmount</l>
               <l>Her necke the Lillies of <hi>Lyguria</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did much exceed; Thus looked fayre <hi>Gyneura.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe Dryades <hi>Diego</hi> then beſpake,</l>
               <l>with ſugred tearmes of mildeſt curteſie,</l>
               <l>And crau'd to know which way he beſt might take</l>
               <l>with ſhorteſt cut, to ſuch a Signiory,</l>
               <l>Whereat he nam'd himſelfe; when preſently</l>
               <l>The Ladies knew him (as a Neyghbour by.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gyneuras</hi> Mother (cheefe of all the reſt)</l>
               <l>(for that ſhee knew his birth and his diſcent)</l>
               <l>Deſir'd him home, he grants her ſuch requeſt,</l>
               <l>and thanks the Fates that him ſuch hap had lent,</l>
               <l>For ſtill on faire <hi>Gyneura</hi> were his eyes,</l>
               <l>And ſhee reciprocally on his replyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:25"/>
               <l>Theſe dumbe Embaſſadors, Loues chiefe combatants</l>
               <l>tell (ſoftly whiſpring in each others hart)</l>
               <l>Her of humble ſeruice; him of acceptance;</l>
               <l>his craued loue, hers wiſht they nere might part,</l>
               <l>Much talk they had w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tongues, more w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their eyes,</l>
               <l>But (oh) moſt with their harts, where true loue lies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now were they come whereas the good old Lady</l>
               <l>might boldly welcome her inuited gueſt,</l>
               <l>Where after little talke, (Hunters are hungry)</l>
               <l>they all ſat downe vnto a ſoone-made feaſt,</l>
               <l>The Louers fed on glaunces of their eyes,</l>
               <l>Tis heauenly food when both do ſimpathize.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt, the Lady of the houſe eſpied</l>
               <l>the intercourſe of thoſe bright Meſſengers,</l>
               <l>Who inwardly reioycing, as faſt plied</l>
               <l>hers on her daughter, fitteſt Harbengers,</l>
               <l>To bid her keepe the faireſt and the beſt</l>
               <l>Place in her hart, to entertaine this gueſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Word back againe was ſent by her faire light,</l>
               <l>how that was done already; and replied,</l>
               <l>The Land-lord o're his Tennant hath ſuch might,</l>
               <l>that he to enter in is nere denied.</l>
               <l>I, in a little corner of my hart</l>
               <l>Doe liue, (quoth ſhe) he hath the greateſt part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:26"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diego</hi> wiſht thys ſupper nere would end,</l>
               <l>(and yet he long'd to be in priuate place,</l>
               <l>To ruminate vpon his faireſt friend,</l>
               <l>and to recount the beauties of her face)</l>
               <l>So wiſht <hi>Gyneura,</hi> were neuer ſuch two,</l>
               <l>That lou'd ſo deerely as theſe Louers doe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The gloomy Curtaines of the tongue-leſſe night,</l>
               <l>were drawne ſo cloſe as day could not be ſeene,</l>
               <l>Now leaden-thoughted <hi>Morpheus</hi> dyms each ſight,</l>
               <l>now, murder, rapes, and robberies begin:</l>
               <l>Nature crau'd reſt, but reſtleſſe Loue would none,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diego,</hi> Loues young prentice, thus gan mone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh heauens, what new-ſounde griefes poſſeſſe my mind,</l>
               <l>what rare impaſsionated fits be theſe?</l>
               <l>Cold-burning Feuers in my hart I find,</l>
               <l>whoſe oppoſite effects worke mee no eaſe,</l>
               <l>Then loue aſſailes the hart with hoteſt fight,</l>
               <l>VVhen beauty makes her conquſt at firſt ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I little dreamed of thys ſtrange euent,</l>
               <l>(this harts-inthraller, mindes-diſturbing Loue,</l>
               <l>VVhen with my Huntſmen to the woods I went,</l>
               <l>Oh neere till now did I his greatnes proue,</l>
               <l>Whoſe firſt impreſſion in the Louers hart,</l>
               <l>Till then nere tainted, bringeth deepeſt ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:26"/>
               <l>Thus lay <hi>Diego</hi> toſſing in his bed,</l>
               <l>bound to the will of all commaunding beauty,</l>
               <l>Whom angry <hi>Cupid</hi> now in tryumph led,</l>
               <l>expecting from his ſlaue all ſeruile duty,</l>
               <l>Hee might haue freed his pryſoner ſo diſmaid,</l>
               <l>For ſighes and grones had double ranſome paide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In like extreames, (Loue loues extremity)</l>
               <l>did faire <hi>Gyneura</hi> paſſe the long-thought night,</l>
               <l>Shee raild againſt fell <hi>Cupids</hi> crueltie,</l>
               <l>that ſo would tyrannize o're a Maydens ſpright.</l>
               <l>There needes no blowes, quoth ſhe, when foes doe yield,</l>
               <l>Oh ceaſe, take thou the honor of the field.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The valiant Greekes (faire Ilyons fatall Foes)</l>
               <l>their tedious ten yeres ſiedge for Spartaes Queen</l>
               <l>Nere thought ſo long; (yet long, it was) as thoſe</l>
               <l>loue-ſcorcht enamored (ſo reſtles) now ween</l>
               <l>This night to be; A night if ſpent in care,</l>
               <l>Seemes longer then a thouſand pleaſant are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus lay they ſleepleſſe, thoughtfull, euer thinking</l>
               <l>on ſluggiſh humor of expected Morne,</l>
               <l>They thought that Louers eyes were neuer winking</l>
               <l>nor ſleepe they e're in whom Loues newly borne.</l>
               <l>Hee vow'd, when day was come, to woo his deere,</l>
               <l>Shee ſwore ſuch wooing ſhe would gladly heare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:27"/>
               <l>At laſt, the guyder of the firie Coach,</l>
               <l>drying his locks wet in <hi>Eurotus</hi> floud,</l>
               <l>Gan reſaluce the world with bright approch,</l>
               <l>angry he ſeem'd, for all his face was bloud:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurorites</hi> haſt had made him looke ſo red,</l>
               <l>For loath he was to leaue faire <hi>Thetis</hi> bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Scarce were his horſes put in readines,</l>
               <l>and he himſelfe full mounted on his ſeate,</l>
               <l>VVhen <hi>Dom Diego</hi> full of heauines,</l>
               <l>abroade did walke, his night talke to repeate:</l>
               <l>Some two howres ſpent, he in againe retires,</l>
               <l>And ſees his Miſtres, whom he now admires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereat inflam'd, (loue brookes no baſe delay,</l>
               <l>whoſe fruite is danger, whoſe reward is paine)</l>
               <l>With fine-fil'd termes he giues her the good day,</l>
               <l>and bluſhing, ſhe returnes it him againe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Endimeons</hi> bluſh her beauty did eclypſe,</l>
               <l>His cauſd by <hi>Cynthiaes,</hi> hers <hi>Adonis</hi> lyps.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Boldly encourag'd by her milde aſpect,</l>
               <l>he told her that which Louers vſe to tell,</l>
               <l>How he did liue by her faire eyes reflect,</l>
               <l>and how his hart in midſt of hers did dwell:</l>
               <l>Much eloquence he vſd, twas needles done,</l>
               <l>To win that hart which was already won.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:27"/>
               <l>Ne're did the dungeon thiefe condemn'd to dye</l>
               <l>with greater pleaſure heare his pardon read,</l>
               <l>Then did <hi>Gyneura</hi> heare his Oratorie,</l>
               <l>(of force ſufficient to reuiue the dead)</l>
               <l>Shee needes muſt yield; for ſure he had the Art,</l>
               <l>VVith amorous heate to fixe <hi>Dianaes</hi> hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe Louers (thus in this both-pleaſing parly)</l>
               <l>were interrupted by <hi>Geneuraes</hi> Mother</l>
               <l>VVho newly vp, (age ſeldome ryſeth early)</l>
               <l>gan ſtraight ſalute her gueſt, ſo did he her,</l>
               <l>Some termes of kindnes mutually paſt,</l>
               <l>Shee friendly leades him in, to breake his faſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhich done, (as all good manners did require)</l>
               <l>hee thankt his Hoſtis for her curteſie,</l>
               <l>And now at length went home for to retire,</l>
               <l>where hee was looked for ſo earneſtly,</l>
               <l>The Lady crau'd if ere hee came that way,</l>
               <l>To ſee her houſe, and there to make ſome ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then heauily, and with a dying eye,</l>
               <l>(ioyleſſe) hee takes his leaue of his faire Loue,</l>
               <l>VVho for to fauour him, full graciouſly,</l>
               <l>with louing count'nance gaue to him her Gloue.</l>
               <l>Keepe this (quoth ſhee) till better fortune fall,</l>
               <l>My Gloue, my Loue, my hand, my hart, and all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:28"/>
               <l>At this large offer, baſhfull modeſtie,</l>
               <l>with pure Vermilion ſtain'd her all faire face,</l>
               <l>So lookt <hi>Calyſtome</hi> at her great bellie,</l>
               <l>when chaſt <hi>Ilythia</hi> ſpi'd her in ſuch caſe;</l>
               <l>Let Louers iudge how grieuous us to part,</l>
               <l>From two, twixt whom, there lyueth but one hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nowe is hee gone, who after little trauell</l>
               <l>attain'd his houſe (not pleaſing thought deſired)</l>
               <l>At whoſe late abſence each one much did maruell,</l>
               <l>but (come) at his ſad lookes they more admired,</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Cupids</hi> power, ſuch ſadnes in him bred,</l>
               <l>VVho (erſt) all louing harts in tryumph led.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One month (conſum'd in penſiuenes) expir'd;</l>
               <l>to recreate and reuiue his tyred ſpright,</l>
               <l>Hee now on hunting goes, which hee deſir'd,</l>
               <l>not for the (once well-pleaſing) ſports delight;</l>
               <l>But for he might ſome fit occaſion finde,</l>
               <l>To ſee his Loue, on whom was all his minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where being come (ſuppoſe his ſports prou'd bad)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gyneura</hi> gaue him welcome from her hart,</l>
               <l>The Sea-toſt Lord of <hi>Ithica</hi> ne're had,</l>
               <l>after his twentie yeares turmoile and ſmart,</l>
               <l>More ioyfull welcome by his conſtant wife</l>
               <l>Then had <hi>Diego</hi> from his loue, his lyfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:28"/>
               <l>Two dayes he ſtay'd, whence he would ne're depart</l>
               <l>but cuſtome wil'd that he ſhould now returne,</l>
               <l>Yet though he went he left with her his hart,</l>
               <l>which for their parting heauily gan mourne,</l>
               <l>But far worſe newes had it poore hart to greeue,</l>
               <l>In that <hi>Gyneura</hi> would ſo ſoone beleeue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For ſooner was hee not departed thence</l>
               <l>but ſtraight there comes a Riuall of his Loue,</l>
               <l>VVho vnder true fidellities pretence</l>
               <l>wrought wondrous hard <hi>Diego</hi> to remoue,</l>
               <l>Nor could at firſt his oaths or vowes preuaile,</l>
               <l>To make <hi>Gyneuraes</hi> loue one whit to faile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For yet they lyu'd faſt bound in Fancies chaines,</l>
               <l>ſtryuing to paſſe each other in pure loue,</l>
               <l>But (as there's nothing that for aye remaines</l>
               <l>without ſome change.) ſo do theſe Louers proue,</l>
               <l>That hotteſt loue hath ſoon'ſt the cold'ſt diſdaine,</l>
               <l>And greateſt pleaſures, haue their greateſt paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For now no longer could ſhee ſo perſeuer,</l>
               <l>ſhee turnes to deadly hate her former kindnes,</l>
               <l>Which ſtill had laſted; but that Nature euer</l>
               <l>ſtrikes into womens eyes ſuch dim-ſight blindnes,</l>
               <l>And ſuch obdurate hardnes in their harts,</l>
               <l>They ſee, nor knowe, not trueſt loues deſarts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:29"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gyneura</hi> this confirmes againſt her Louer,</l>
               <l>whom now (all guiltleſſe) ſhe condemnes to die,</l>
               <l>That in his deede or thought did nere offend her,</l>
               <l>vnleſſe by louing her ſo wondrous deerelie:</l>
               <l>Such Loue, ſuch hate, ſuch lyking, ſuch diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Was neuer knowne in one hart to remaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus twas; <hi>Diego</hi> had an enemie,</l>
               <l>(immortall vertue euer lincked is,</l>
               <l>With that pale leane-fac'd meager-hewed enuie)</l>
               <l>who ſecretly (ſo falſely) tells his Mis.</l>
               <l>How ſhee was mockt; <hi>Diego</hi> lou'd another,</l>
               <l>And ſtorm'd &amp; rag'd what madnes ſo ſhould moue her</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To dote on him that elſe where ſets his Loue,</l>
               <l>hee makes you thinke (quoth he) what ere he liſt,</l>
               <l>That this is true, you eaſily may proue</l>
               <l>for ſtill he weares her fauour on his fiſt,</l>
               <l>A Hawke it is; which ſhee (ſo ſtands the Mart)</l>
               <l>Giues him, he you faire words, but her his hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVith this incenſt, (that ſex will ſoone beleeue)</l>
               <l>ſooneſt when enuies broode to them diſplay it,</l>
               <l>I'ſt true (quoth ſhee) for true loue doth he giue,</l>
               <l>ſuch ſmooth-fac'd flattry, doth he thus repay it?</l>
               <l>Shee neuer ſcan'd, the truth of this her griefe,</l>
               <l>Loue in ſuch caſes, is of quicke beliefe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:29"/>
               <l>Her loue to him was neuer halfe ſo great,</l>
               <l>(though once ſhee lou'd him) as is now her hate,</l>
               <l>This <hi>Momus</hi> breath (like bellowes) to her heate,</l>
               <l>did kindle firie coales of hote debate.</l>
               <l>Hee plyes her; and exaſperates his ſpight,</l>
               <l>And ſweares, and vowes, hee tells her but the right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee (like a franticke Froe of <hi>Theſſaly</hi>
               </l>
               <l>madded with <hi>Bacchus</hi> brayne-diſtempring liquor)</l>
               <l>Runs here, and there, exclayming furiouſly</l>
               <l>with hideous, vncouth mind-affrighting terror.</l>
               <l>Swearing reuenge on falſe <hi>Diegoes</hi> head,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe lying lookes in her ſuch madnes bred.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVherewith ſhee inuocates great <hi>Nemeſis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>and begs the power of her deitie,</l>
               <l>Shee tells her caſe, to Iuſtice-doing <hi>Themis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>and ſhewes how ſhee is wronged mightily.</l>
               <l>Shee leaues no power vnſought for, or vnpraide,</l>
               <l>That vſe to helpe diſtreſſed with their aide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wronged <hi>Diego</hi> (little this ſuſpecting)</l>
               <l>now thought it time to ſee his deereſt faire,</l>
               <l>And (other matters of import neglecting,</l>
               <l>hee preſently to her makes his repaire.</l>
               <l>VVhere being come, ſuch welcome he did finde,</l>
               <l>As at the firſt did much diſturbe his minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:30"/>
               <l>For faire <hi>Gyneura</hi> would not now be ſeene,</l>
               <l>ſhe ſent him word ſhe ſcorn'd his fauning flattrie,</l>
               <l>And much did greeue, that ſhee ſo fond had beene,</l>
               <l>to yield her hart to ſuch deceitfull battrie:</l>
               <l>Bid him (quoth ſhee) goe flatter where he liſt,</l>
               <l>I like not I, that fauour on his fiſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such hap it was, <hi>Diego</hi> then had brought</l>
               <l>his Hawke; (the author of this fell debate)</l>
               <l>Which well confirm'd her euer doubtfull thought,</l>
               <l>that nowe ſhee was reſolu'd on deadly hate,</l>
               <l>Bid him (quoth ſhe) depart hence from my ſight,</l>
               <l>His loath-ſome preſence brings me irkſome ſpight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Twas hard; that he whoſe loue was neuer tainted</l>
               <l>whoſe ſincere faith was kept inuiolate,</l>
               <l>Nay, in whoſe face all trueſt loue was painted,</l>
               <l>ſhould for his ſpotleſſe truth be paid with hate,</l>
               <l>Hee ſtone-aſtonied, like a Deare at gaze,</l>
               <l>Admir'd theſe ſpeeches in a wondrous maze.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt hee crau'd this fauour be might haue,</l>
               <l>that ſhee her ſelfe would heare what he could ſay,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Neptunes</hi> Towne (quoth ſhee) ſuch lycenſe gaue</l>
               <l>to ſmooth-fac'd <hi>Synon (Ilions</hi> laſt decay)</l>
               <l>So <hi>Syrens</hi> ſing vntill they haue their will,</l>
               <l>Some poore miſtruſtleſſe Paſſenger to kill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:30"/>
               <l>Shee would not heare him ſpeake (oh cruell ſhee)</l>
               <l>that cauſeleſſe this would kill him with diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Hee ſweares he's guiltleſſe, vowes innocencie,</l>
               <l>&amp; in ſuch vowes, tears down his cheeks did raine,</l>
               <l>Thoſe cheeks which ſtaine the bluſhing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morne</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gyneura</hi> now moſt hatefully doth ſcorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tis ſtrange that Maides ſhould ere be ſo abuſed,</l>
               <l>to credit each malicious-tongued ſlaue,</l>
               <l>And to condemne a man (if once accuſed)</l>
               <l>before or proofe, or tryall, hee may haue.</l>
               <l>Too many ſuch there be; wo's mee therefore,</l>
               <l>Such light credulitie, I muſt deplore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When ſighes, ſalt tears, &amp; vowes could do no good,</l>
               <l>nor ſighes, nor teares, nor vowes could pierce her hart,</l>
               <l>In which, diſdaine triumphant victor ſtood</l>
               <l>holding in eyther hand a ſable dart,</l>
               <l>VVherewith he ſtrikes true loue, &amp; ſtainleſſe truth,</l>
               <l>Condemning them vnto eternall ruth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Home goes <hi>Diego,</hi> with a cheereleſſe face,</l>
               <l>whoſe ſteps were led by leaden-footed griefe,</l>
               <l>VVho neuer goes but with a dead-ſlowe pace,</l>
               <l>vntill hee finde ſome eaſe, or ſome reliefe;</l>
               <l>Twould melt a marble hart to ſee that man,</l>
               <l>(Earſt, freſh as a new-blowne Roſe) ſo aſhie wan.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:31"/>
               <l>VVhere being come, he ſtraight for four daies ſpace,</l>
               <l>locks him in his chamber, and there did poure</l>
               <l>Huge ſhewers of chriſtall rayne adowne his face,</l>
               <l>(for ſure he lou'd her deerely at this howre)</l>
               <l>All ouerwhelm'd in waues of ſea-ſalt teares,</l>
               <l>Some fatall ſhipwrack of his life he feares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherewith he calls for paper, pen, and yuck,</l>
               <l>and for his Hawke, which preſently he kild,</l>
               <l>Die thou (quoth he) ſo ſhall my loue nere thinke,</l>
               <l>that for thy ſake to any elſe I yield.</l>
               <l>And plucking of her head, ſtraight way hee writes,</l>
               <l>VVho (ſending it as token) thus indites.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Loe heere (thou cruell faire) that gracious fauour,</l>
               <l>the Enſigne (as thou ſaiſt) of my vntruth,</l>
               <l>Behold in what high-priz'd eſteeme I haue her</l>
               <l>that gaue me it, the cauſe of all my ruth:</l>
               <l>Looke as this Hawke, faire Loue, ſo is my hart,</l>
               <l>Mangled and torne, cauſe thou ſo cruell art.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſweare to thee by all the rites of loue,</l>
               <l>by heauens faire head, by earth, &amp; black-fac'd hel,</l>
               <l>I nere meant other loue but thine to proue,</l>
               <l>nor in my hart that any elſe ſhould dwell;</l>
               <l>Let this ſuffize, my ioy, my deere, my chiefe,</l>
               <l>My griefes are too too long, though letter briefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:31"/>
               <l>Twas time to ende, for floods guſht out amaine,</l>
               <l>out came the ſpringtide of his briniſh teares,</l>
               <l>VVhich whatſoere hee writ blot out againe</l>
               <l>all blubred ſo to ſend it ſcarce hee dares:</l>
               <l>And yet hee did; goe thou (quoth hee) vnto her,</l>
               <l>And for thy maiſter, treate, ſollicite, woo her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And pray thee (if thy Fortune be ſo good</l>
               <l>as to be viewd by ſunſhine of her eyes)</l>
               <l>Bid her take heede in ſpilling guiltleſſe blood,</l>
               <l>tell her there's danger in ſuch cruelties:</l>
               <l>VVith this, hee gaue it to the meſſenger,</l>
               <l>Who (making ſpeed) in ſhort time brought it her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee, when ſhee heard from whom the Letter came,</l>
               <l>returnes it backe againe, and ſtraight replied,</l>
               <l>My friend (quoth ſhe) hadſt thou not told his name</l>
               <l>perhaps thy Letter, had not beene denied:</l>
               <l>VVhereat ſhee paus'd; but yet ile ſee (quoth ſhee)</l>
               <l>With what perſwading termes, he flatters mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Twas quickly read; (God knowes it was but ſhort)</l>
               <l>griefe would not let the wryter tedious be,</l>
               <l>Nor would it ſuffer him fit words to ſort,</l>
               <l>but pens it (chaoſ-like) confuſedly.</l>
               <l>Yet had it paſſion to haue turn'd hard ſtones</l>
               <l>To liquid moiſture, if they heard his moanes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:32"/>
               <l>But cruell ſhee, more hard then any flint,</l>
               <l>worſe then a Tygreſſe of Hyrcania,</l>
               <l>Would not be mou'd, nor could his lines take print</l>
               <l>in her hard hurt, ſo cruell was <hi>Gyneura.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shee which once lou'd him deerly, (too too well)</l>
               <l>Now hates him more then any tongue can tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh Nature, chiefeſt Mother of vs all,</l>
               <l>why did you giue ſuch apt-beleeuing harts</l>
               <l>To women-kind, that thus poore men inthrall,</l>
               <l>and will not dulie waie true loues deſarts?</l>
               <l>O had their harts been like vnto their face,</l>
               <l>They ſure had been of ſome celeſtiall race.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee pittiles, ſends backe to <hi>Dom Diego,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>and ſayes, his words cannot inchant her hart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vliſſes</hi>-like, ſhee will not heare <hi>Calypſo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>nor lend her eares to ſuch intiſing arte.</l>
               <l>Bid him (quoth ſhe) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth ceaſe to write,</l>
               <l>Tell him his Letters agrauate my ſpight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Full heauie newes it was to ſtaineleſſe loue,</l>
               <l>to him that had enſhrin'd her in his thought,</l>
               <l>And in his hart had honor'd her aboue</l>
               <l>the world; to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all elſe ſaue her ſeem'd nought.</l>
               <l>Nay, vnto him, whoſe perſon, wit, and faire,</l>
               <l>Might ſurely with the beſt make iuſt compare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:32"/>
               <l>But (blinded as ſhee was) ſhee ſteemes him not,</l>
               <l>hate and diſdaine doe neuer brooke reſpect,</l>
               <l>Shee did not knowe that beauties fouleſt blot</l>
               <l>conſiſted in true-louing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rts neglect.</l>
               <l>No, ſhe (more ſtubborne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the North-eaſt wind)</l>
               <l>VVould not admit ſuch knowledge in her mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let thoſe who guiltleſſlie haue felt diſdaine,</l>
               <l>whoſe faithfull loue hath beene repaid with hate,</l>
               <l>Giue rightfull iudgement of <hi>Diegoes</hi> paine</l>
               <l>who bought his fauours at the higheſt rate.</l>
               <l>This newes ſuch pleaſure in his ſoule had bred,</l>
               <l>As hath the thiefe that hearts his iudgement read.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>After ſome time, hee writes againe vnto her,</l>
               <l>hee could not thinke ſhee would perſeuer ſo,</l>
               <l>But when hee ſawe her aunſwere like the other</l>
               <l>hee then ſurceas'd to ſend her any moe.</l>
               <l>But did reſolue to ſeeke ſome vncouth place,</l>
               <l>VVhere he might (vnfound out) bewaile his caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinking indeede; ſhee by his abſence might</l>
               <l>at length intenerate her flintfull hart,</l>
               <l>And metamorphize her conceaued ſpight</l>
               <l>into true loue regardaunt of his ſmart;</l>
               <l>Hee ſeekes all meanes (poore Louer) how to gaine</l>
               <l>His rigorous Lady from ſuch fell diſdaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:33"/>
               <l>At laſt, hee calls to mind the Pyren Mountaines,</l>
               <l>thoſe far-fam'd, woody hills of wealthy Spaine,</l>
               <l>Which for wild Beaſts, &amp; ſiluer viſag'd Fountaines,</l>
               <l>hath got the praiſe of all that there remaine:</l>
               <l>Hether poſtes <hi>Dom Diego</hi> fraught with griefe,</l>
               <l>Hoping thoſe woods would yield him ſome reliefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhere, being come, all Pilgrim-like attir'd,</l>
               <l>hee pryes about to ſee if hee could finde,</l>
               <l>Some houſe-like Caue, for reſt hee much deſir'd,</l>
               <l>his body now was wearie, as his minde.</l>
               <l>O Gods (quoth hee) if youth finde ſuch diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>VVhat hope haue I, of future happines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVith that hee ſees a Rocke made like a Cabin</l>
               <l>all tapiſtred with Natures moſſie greene,</l>
               <l>VVrought in a frizled guiſe, as it had been</l>
               <l>made for <hi>Napaea,</hi> Mountaines chiefeſt Queene,</l>
               <l>At mouth of which grew Cedars, Pines, &amp; Firs,</l>
               <l>And at the top grew Maple, Yough, and Poplers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So, heere (quoth hee) ile reſt my wearied bodie</l>
               <l>in thee (delightfull place of Natures building)</l>
               <l>VVill I erect a griefe-fram'd Monaſterie,</l>
               <l>where night &amp; day my prayers ile ne're ceaſe yielding,</l>
               <l>To thee my decre; (no other Saint I haue)</l>
               <l>Oh lend thine eares, to him that his hart gaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:33"/>
               <l>Two dayes were ſpent in this ſo pleaſant ſeate,</l>
               <l>(this ſtone-built Pallace of the King content)</l>
               <l>Before <hi>Diego</hi> taſted any meate,</l>
               <l>or once did drinke, more then his eyes had lent.</l>
               <l>O irreſiſted force of pureſt Loue,</l>
               <l>Whom paines, thirſt, hunger, can no whit remoue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sometimes, when as he ſcans her crueltie,</l>
               <l>&amp; feeles his paines (like <hi>Hydreas</hi> head) increaſing,</l>
               <l>Hee wiſht the Scithian <hi>Anthropophagie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>did haunt theſe woods that liue by mans fleſh eating;</l>
               <l>Or elſe the Thracian <hi>Beſſi,</hi> ſo renound,</l>
               <l>For cruell murdring, whom in woods they found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ſo the <hi>Gordyon</hi> knot of his paine</l>
               <l>indiſſoluble e're whiles he did lyue,</l>
               <l>Might be vntide when as his hart were ſlaine,</l>
               <l>when he (ô reſtfull time) ſhold ceaſe to grieue;</l>
               <l>But yet the Siſters kept his vitall breath,</l>
               <l>They would not let him dye ſo baſe a death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some other times when as he waies her beautie,</l>
               <l>her <hi>Venus</hi>-ſtayning face ſo wondrous faire,</l>
               <l>Hee then doth thinke to waile tis but his dutie</l>
               <l>ſith caus'd by her that is without compaire,</l>
               <l>And in this moode vnto high <hi>Ioue</hi> hee prayes,</l>
               <l>And praying ſo, hee thus vnto him ſayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:34"/>
               <l>Great Gouernour of (wheele-reſembling) Heauen,</l>
               <l>commaund thy vnder Princes to mayntaine,</l>
               <l>Thoſe heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly parts which to my loue th'aue giuen,</l>
               <l>ô let her ne're feele death, or deaths fell paine.</l>
               <l>And firſt vpon thy Siſter lay thy mace,</l>
               <l>Bid her maintayne my Loues maieſtick grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Inioyne the ſtrange-borne mother-leſſe <hi>Mynerua,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>and her to whom the fomie Sea was Mother,</l>
               <l>Still to vphold their giftes in my <hi>Gyneura:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>let wit and beautie lyue vnited with her;</l>
               <l>With ſweete mouth'd <hi>Pytho</hi> I may not ſuſpence,</l>
               <l>Great Goddeſſe, ſtill increaſe her eloquence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou muſicall <hi>Apollo</hi> gau'ſt her hand,</l>
               <l>and thou her feete (great Sun-Gods deereſt loue)</l>
               <l>To ſuch your rare-knowne gyfts all gracious ſtand;</l>
               <l>and now at laſt this doe I craue great <hi>Ioue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That when they dye (perhaps they dye aboue)</l>
               <l>Thou wilt bequeath theſe gyfts vnto my Loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On euery neighbour Tree, on euery ſtone</l>
               <l>(hee durſt not far range from his ſecure Caue)</l>
               <l>VVould he cut out the cauſe of all his moane,</l>
               <l>and curiouſlie with greateſt skill ingraue:</l>
               <l>There needed no <hi>Leontius,</hi> his Art,</l>
               <l>Griefe carueth deepeſt, if it come from th'hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:34"/>
               <l>VVhen ſome ſtone would not impreſſion take</l>
               <l>hee ſtraight compares it to his Miſtris hart,</l>
               <l>But ſtay, (quoth he) my working teares ſhall make</l>
               <l>thee penetrable with the leaſt-skil'd art.</l>
               <l>Oh had my teares ſuch force to pierce her mind,</l>
               <l>Theſe ſorrowes I ſhould looſe, and new ioyes find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou euer-memorable ſtone (quoth hee)</l>
               <l>tell thoſe whom fate or fortune heere ſhall lead,</l>
               <l>How deerely I haue lou'd the cruel'ſt ſhee</l>
               <l>that euer Nature or the world hath bred.</l>
               <l>Tell them her hate, and her diſdaine was cauſeleſſe.</l>
               <l>Oh, leaue not out to tell how I was guiltleſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereat, the very ſtone would ſeeme to weepe,</l>
               <l>whoſe wrinkled face wold be beſmeard with tears</l>
               <l>O man what ere thou be, thy ſorrowes keepe</l>
               <l>vnto thy ſelfe, quoth hee; ile heare no cares.</l>
               <l>Tell them that care not, tell <hi>Gyneura</hi> of thee,</l>
               <l>We ſtones are ruthfull, &amp; thy plaints haue pierc'd mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVith this, hee ſeekes a ruſſet-coated Tree,</l>
               <l>&amp; ſtraight diſclothes him of his long-worne weed</l>
               <l>And whileſt hee thus diſroabes him buſilie,</l>
               <l>hee felt his halfe-dead hart a freſh to bleed.</l>
               <l>Greeuing that hee ſhould vſe ſuch crueltie,</l>
               <l>To turne him naked to his foe, windes furie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:35"/>
               <l>But now vncas'd, hee gins to carue his cares,</l>
               <l>his paſſions, his conſtant-lyuing Loue,</l>
               <l>When (loe) there guſhes out cleere ſap like teares</l>
               <l>which to get forth from pryſon mainly ſtroue,</l>
               <l>Since pitty dwells (quoth hee) in trees and ſtone,</l>
               <l>Them will I loue; <hi>Gyneura,</hi> thou haſt none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet needs I muſt confeſſe thou once didſt loue mee,</l>
               <l>thy loue was hotter then <hi>Nimphaeum</hi> hill,</l>
               <l>But now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time affords me, means to proue thee,</l>
               <l>thy loue then <hi>Caucaſe</hi> is more cold and chill,</l>
               <l>And in thy cold, like Aethiopyan hue,</l>
               <l>Thou art not to be chang'd from falſe to true.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O looke (faire Loue) as in the ſpringing Plant</l>
               <l>one branch intwines and growes within another,</l>
               <l>So growe my griefes; which makes my hart to pant</l>
               <l>when thicke-fetcht ſighes my vitall breath doth ſmother,</l>
               <l>I ſpoild my cruelty am adiudg'd to death,</l>
               <l>Thus all alone to yield my lyuing breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou haſt the fayreſt face that e're was ſeene,</l>
               <l>but in thy breaſt (that Alablaſter Rocke)</l>
               <l>Thou haſt a fouler hart; diſdaine hath beene</l>
               <l>accounted blacker then the Chimnies ſtocke.</l>
               <l>O purifie thy ſoule my deareſt Loue,</l>
               <l>Diſlodge thy hate, and thy diſdaine remoue,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:35"/>
               <l>But all in vaine I ſpeake vnto the wind,</l>
               <l>then ſhould they carry theſe my plaints vnto her,</l>
               <l>Mee thinks thou ſtill ſhouldſt beare a gentle mind,</l>
               <l>(deere louing <hi>Zephire</hi>) pray, intreate, &amp; woo her;</l>
               <l>Tell her twere pittie I ſhould dye alone,</l>
               <l>Here in theſe woods wher non can heare me mone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But tis no matter, ſhee is pittyleſſe</l>
               <l>like the Scycilian ſtone that more tis beate</l>
               <l>Doth waxe the harder; ſtones are not ſo ruthleſſe,</l>
               <l>which ſmalleſt drops doe pierce though nere ſo great;</l>
               <l>If Seas of teares would weare into her hart,</l>
               <l>I had ere this beene eaſed of my ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus in theſe ſpeeches would <hi>Diego</hi> ſit</l>
               <l>bathing his ſiluer cheekes with trickling teares,</l>
               <l>VVhich (often running downe) at laſt found fit</l>
               <l>channells to ſend them to their ſtanding meares,</l>
               <l>VVho at his feete (before his feete there ſtood</l>
               <l>A poole of teares) receau'd the ſmaller flood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ne're had the world a truer louing hart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abydos</hi> ceaſe to ſpeake of conſtant loue,</l>
               <l>Por ſure (thou Sygnior <hi>Dom Diego</hi>) art</l>
               <l>the onely man that e're hates force did proue;</l>
               <l>Thy changeleſſe loue hath cloſe inrol'd thy name,</l>
               <l>In ſteele-leau'd booke of euer-lyuing fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:36"/>
               <l>That wide-mouth'd time w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwallows good deſarts</l>
               <l>ſhall ſhut his iawes, &amp; ne're deuoure thy name,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt be crown'd with bayes by louing harts,</l>
               <l>and dwell in Temple of eternall Fame;</l>
               <l>There, is a ſacred place reſeru'd for thee,</l>
               <l>There, thou ſhalt liue with perpetuitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So long liu'd poore <hi>Diego</hi> in this caſe</l>
               <l>that at the length hee waxed ſomwhat bold,</l>
               <l>To ſearch the woods where hee might ſafely chaſe,</l>
               <l>(neceſſitie, thy force cannot be told)</l>
               <l>The fearefull Hare, the Connie, and the Kid,</l>
               <l>Time made him knowe the places where they bid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This young-year'd Hermit, one day mong the reſt</l>
               <l>as hee was buſilie prouiding meate,</l>
               <l>VVhich was with Natures cunning almoſt dreſt,</l>
               <l>dri'd with the Sunne new readie to be eate,</l>
               <l>Inrag'd vpon a ſuddaine throwes away</l>
               <l>His hard-got foode; and thus began to ſay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O cruell ſtarres, Step-mothers of my good,</l>
               <l>&amp; you, you ruthleſſe Fates what meane you thus,</l>
               <l>So greedely to thirſt for my harts blood,</l>
               <l>why ioy you ſo in vnuniting vs?</l>
               <l>Great powres infuſe ſome pitty in her hart</l>
               <l>That thus hath cauſeleſſe caus'd in me this ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:36"/>
               <l>I ne're was wont to vſe ſuch Cookerie,</l>
               <l>to drudge &amp; toile whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peſants take their pleaſure,</l>
               <l>My noble birth ſcornes baſe-borne ſlauerie,</l>
               <l>this eaſeleſſe lyfe hath neither end nor meaſure;</l>
               <l>Thou great <hi>Soſipolis</hi> looke vpon my ſtate,</l>
               <l>Be of theſe nere-hard griefes compaſſionate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I feele my long-thought life begin to melt</l>
               <l>as doth the ſnowe gainſt midday heate of Sunne,</l>
               <l>(Faire loue) thy rigour I haue too much felt,</l>
               <l>oh, at the laſt with crueltie haue done,</l>
               <l>If teares thy ſtonie hart could mollifie,</l>
               <l>My briniſh ſprings ſhould floe eternallie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sweet loue, behold thoſe pale cheekes waſht in woe</l>
               <l>that ſo my teares may as a mirror be,</l>
               <l>Thine owne faire ſhaddowe liuely for to ſhoe,</l>
               <l>and portraite forth thy Angel-hued beautie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Narciſſus</hi>-lyke then ſhouldſt thou my face kiſſe,</l>
               <l>More honny ſweete, then <hi>Venus</hi> gaue <hi>Adonis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Feare not <hi>Gyneura,</hi> faire <hi>Narciſſus</hi> hap;</l>
               <l>thy necke, thy breaſt, thy hand is Lilly-white,</l>
               <l>They all are Lillies tane from <hi>Floraes</hi> lap;</l>
               <l>ne're be thou chang'd vnleſſe to loue from ſpite.</l>
               <l>Oh that thou wer't but then transformed ſo,</l>
               <l>My Sommers bliſſe, would change my winters woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:37"/>
               <l>If thou did'ſt knowe in what a loathſome place,</l>
               <l>I ſpend my dayes ſad and diſconſolate,</l>
               <l>VVhat foggie Stigian miſts hang o're my face,</l>
               <l>thou would'ſt exile this thy conceaued hate;</l>
               <l>This Hemiſphere is darke, for <hi>Sol</hi> him ſhroudes,</l>
               <l>My ſighes doe ſo conglomerate the cloudes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I tolde thee, I, (thou cruell too ſeuere)</l>
               <l>when hate firſt gan to riſe how I was guiltleſſe,</l>
               <l>Thine eares were deaffe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would'ſt not harken ere thee,</l>
               <l>thy hart was hardned, rockie, pittileſſe.</l>
               <l>Oh had mine eyes been blind whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt they view'd</l>
               <l>Would God I had been tongleſſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſew'd thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou waſt then as readie to receaue</l>
               <l>as I to craue; ô great inconſtancie,</l>
               <l>O twas that fatall houre did ſo bereaue</l>
               <l>my blisfull ſoule of all tranquillitie:</l>
               <l>Thou then didſt burne in loue, now froz'd in hate,</l>
               <l>Yet pittie mee, ſweete mercy ne're comes late.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke as the crazen tops of armeleſſe Trees</l>
               <l>or lateſt down-fall of ſome aged building,</l>
               <l>Doe tell thee of the North-windes boiſtrous furies,</l>
               <l>and how that <hi>Eolus</hi> lately hath beene ſtirring;</l>
               <l>So in my thin cheekt face thou well maiſt ſee,</l>
               <l>The furious ſtorme of thy black crueltie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:37"/>
               <l>But thou inexorable art, ne're to be wone,</l>
               <l>though Lyons, Bears, &amp; Tigers haue been tam'd,</l>
               <l>Thy wood-borne rigour neuer will be done,</l>
               <l>which thinks for this thou euer ſhalt be fam'd;</l>
               <l>True, ſo thou ſhalt, but fam'd in infamie,</l>
               <l>Is worſe then lyuing in obſcuritie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thou didſt knowe howe greeuous tis to me</l>
               <l>to lyue in this vnhabited aboade,</l>
               <l>Where none (but ſorrowe) keepes me companie,</l>
               <l>I know thou wouldſt thy harts hate then vnload,</l>
               <l>Oh, I did ne're deſerue this miſerie,</l>
               <l>For to denie the truth were hereſie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I tell thee (Loue) when ſecret-tongued night</l>
               <l>puts on her miſtie ſable-coloured vayle,</l>
               <l>My wrangling woes, within them ſelues do fight,</l>
               <l>they murder hope, which makes their Captaine wayle,</l>
               <l>And wailing ſo, can neuer take his reſt,</l>
               <l>That keepes ſuch vnrul'd Souldiers in his breſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So when the cleere nights-faults-diſcloſing day</l>
               <l>peepes forth her purple head, from out the Eaſt,</l>
               <l>Theſe woes (my Souldiers) crie out for their pay,</l>
               <l>(and if deni'd) they ſtab mee, with vnreſt;</l>
               <l>My teares are pay, but all my teates are dri'de</l>
               <l>Therefore I muſt their fatall blowes abide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:38"/>
               <l>In theſe laments did <hi>Dom Diego</hi> liue</l>
               <l>long time; till at the laſt by pourefull fate,</l>
               <l>A wandring Huntſman ignorance did driue</l>
               <l>vnto the place whence hee return'd but late;</l>
               <l>Who viewing well the print of humaine ſteps</l>
               <l>Directly followed them, and for ioy leaps.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt hee came vnto <hi>Diegoes</hi> Caue</l>
               <l>in which he ſawe a ſauadge man (hee thought)</l>
               <l>Who much did looke like the <hi>Danubyan</hi> ſlaue,</l>
               <l>ſuch deep-worn furrows in his face were wrought,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diego</hi> much abaſhed at this ſight</l>
               <l>Came running forth, him in his armes to plight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For glad hee was (God knowes) to ſee a man,</l>
               <l>who (wretch) in two yeres ſpace did ne're ſee any</l>
               <l>Such gladnes, ioy, ſuch mirth, ſuch triumph can</l>
               <l>not be ſet downe, ſuppoſe them to be many.</l>
               <l>But ſee, long had they not confer'd together,</l>
               <l>When (happie time) each one did know the other.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVith that <hi>Diego</hi> ſhewes him all his loue,</l>
               <l>his pennance, her firſt loue, &amp; now her hate,</l>
               <l>But hee requeſted him hence to remoue,</l>
               <l>and at his houſe the reſt hee ſhould dilate,</l>
               <l>Which hee deni'd, onely hee now doth write</l>
               <l>By this his friend, vnto his harts delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:38"/>
               <l>Deere Loue (quoth he) when ſhall I home returne,</l>
               <l>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will the coales of hate be quencht with loue,</l>
               <l>VVhich now in raging flames my hart do burne,</l>
               <l>oh, when wilt thou this thy diſdaine remoue;</l>
               <l>Aske of this bearer, be inquiſitiue,</l>
               <l>And hee will tell thee in what caſe I liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Inquire of her, whoſe Hawke hath caus'd this woe,</l>
               <l>if for that fauour euer I did loue her,</l>
               <l>And ſhee will curſe mee that did vſe her ſo,</l>
               <l>and ſhee will tell thee how I lou'd another;</l>
               <l>Twas thee <hi>Gyueura,</hi> twas thy faireſt ſelfe,</l>
               <l>I hel'd thee as a Pearle, her droſſie pelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, when thou haſt found out the naked truth,</l>
               <l>thinke of thy <hi>Diego,</hi> and his hard hap,</l>
               <l>Let it procure in thee ſome mouing ruth,</l>
               <l>that thus haſt cauſeleſſe caſt him from thy lap:</l>
               <l>Fare-well my deere, I hope this ſhall ſuffize,</l>
               <l>To ad a period to thy cruelties.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Meſſenger to ſpurre forth her deſires,</l>
               <l>and haſten her vnto his well-lou'd friend,</l>
               <l>Tells her, how hee lyes languiſhing in fires</l>
               <l>of burning griefes, which neuer will haue end:</l>
               <l>Bids her to flye to him with wings of zeale,</l>
               <l>And thus <hi>Diegoes</hi> paines hee doth reueale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:39"/>
               <l>Oh Adamantick-minded Mayde (quoth hee)</l>
               <l>why linger you in this ambiguous thought,</l>
               <l>Open thine eyes, no longer blinded bee,</l>
               <l>thoſe wounding lookes, thy Louer, deere hath bought.</l>
               <l>Vnbolt thy harts ſtrong gate of hardeſt ſteele,</l>
               <l>O let him nowe the warmth of pittie feele.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh let him now the warmth of pittie feele,</l>
               <l>that long hath knockt cold-ſtaruen at thy dore;</l>
               <l>Wanting loues foode hee here &amp; there doth reele</l>
               <l>lyke to a ſtorme-toſt Ship that's far from ſhore.</l>
               <l>Feede him with loue that long hath fed on cares,</l>
               <l>Be Anchor to his ſoule that ſwims in teares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gyneura,</hi> let him harbour in thy hart</l>
               <l>rig and amend his trouble-beaten face,</l>
               <l>O calme thy hate, whoſe winds haue rais'd his ſmart</l>
               <l>ſee him not perriſh in this wofull caſe.</l>
               <l>And for in Sea-ſalt teares hee long hath liu'd,</l>
               <l>Let him by thy freſh water be relieu'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh, ſhall I tell thee how I found him there,</l>
               <l>his houſe wherein hee liu'd (if lyue hee did,</l>
               <l>Or rather ſpend his time in dying feare)</l>
               <l>was built within the ground, all darkſom hid,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Phoebus</hi> light, ſo vgly, hell-lyke Caue,</l>
               <l>In all the world againe you cannot haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:39"/>
               <l>All made of rug'd hard-fauour'd ſtones,</l>
               <l>whoſe churliſh lookes afford the eye no pleaſure,</l>
               <l>In whoſe concauity winds breath'd horce grones,</l>
               <l>to which ſad muſicke Sorrow daunc'd a meaſure.</l>
               <l>O'regrowne it was with mighty ſhadefull Trees,</l>
               <l>VVhere poore <hi>Diego</hi> Sun nor Moone nere ſees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To this black place repaired euery morne,</l>
               <l>The fayre <hi>Oreades</hi> pitty-moned gerles,</l>
               <l>Bringing the poore <hi>Diego</hi> ſo forlorne,</l>
               <l>Moſſe to dry vp his teares, thoſe liquid pearles:</l>
               <l>Full loath they were to looſe ſuch chriſtall ſprings,</l>
               <l>Therfore this Spunge-like Moſſe each of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here dry (ſay they) thou loue-forſaken man,</l>
               <l>thoſe glaſſy Conduits, which do neuer ceaſe</l>
               <l>On this ſoft-feeling weede; and if you can,</l>
               <l>we all intreate, your griefes you would appeaſe,</l>
               <l>Elſe wilt thou make vs pine in griefe-full woe,</l>
               <l>That nere knewe care, or loue, or friend, or foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Straight (like a ſhooting Commet in the ayre)</l>
               <l>away depart theſe ſorrow-peirced maydes,</l>
               <l>Leauing <hi>Diego</hi> in a deepe diſpaire,</l>
               <l>who now, his fortune, now his fate vp-braides.</l>
               <l>O heauens (quoth he) how happy are theſe trees,</l>
               <l>That know not loue, nor feele his miſeries.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:40"/>
               <l>Melts not thy hart <hi>(Gyneura)</hi> at his cares?</l>
               <l>are not thy bright tranſparent eyes yet blinde</l>
               <l>VVith monſtrous diluge of o'reflowing teares?</l>
               <l>remaines there yet diſdaines within thy mind?</l>
               <l>Diſgorge thy hate, O hate him not that loues thee,</l>
               <l>Maids are more milde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men, yet pitty moues me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Breake, breake in peeces that delicious cheſt,</l>
               <l>whiter then ſnow on Hyperboreall hyll,</l>
               <l>Chaſe out diſdaine, depriue him of his reſt,</l>
               <l>murder and mangle him that rules thy will.</l>
               <l>Be it nere ſayd that faire <hi>Gyneuraes</hi> beauty,</l>
               <l>Was ouer-peiz'd by cauſeleſſe cruelty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cruell to him that merrits curteſie,</l>
               <l>loathed of thee that doth deſerue all loue,</l>
               <l>Baſely reiected, ſcorn'd moſt churliſhly,</l>
               <l>that honors thee aboue the Saints aboue.</l>
               <l>True loue is priceleſſe, rare, and therefore deere,</l>
               <l>VVe feaſt not royall Kings with homely cheere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Too long it were to tell thee all his merrits,</l>
               <l>for in delay conſiſts his long-lookt death,</l>
               <l>Poſt-haſt of thine muſt now reuiue his ſpirits,</l>
               <l>or ſhortly he will gaſpe his lateſt breath;</l>
               <l>Speake faire <hi>Gyneura,</hi> ſpeake as I deſire,</l>
               <l>Or let thy vaine-breath'd ſpeeches back retyre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:40"/>
               <l>Looke, as a man late taken from a trance,</l>
               <l>ſtandes gazing heere and there in ſenceleſſe wiſe,</l>
               <l>Not able of himſelfe his head t'aduance,</l>
               <l>but ſtandeth like a ſtone in death-like guiſe,</l>
               <l>So lookt <hi>Gyneura,</hi> hanging downe her head,</l>
               <l>Shaming that folly her ſo much had led.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Repentant ſorrow would not let her ſpeake,</l>
               <l>the burning flames of griefe did dry her teares,</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt, words out of priſon breake,</l>
               <l>that long'd to vtter her harts inward cares:</l>
               <l>And ſtealingly there glides with heauy pace</l>
               <l>A Riuolet of Pearle along her face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O ceaſe (quoth ſhe) to wound me any more,</l>
               <l>with oft repeating of my cruelties,</l>
               <l>Thou of thy teares (kind man) haſt ſhed great ſtore,</l>
               <l>when I (vnkinder mayde) ſcarce wet mine eyes.</l>
               <l>O let me now bewaile him once for all,</l>
               <l>Twas none but I that cauſd his cauſeleſſe thrall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eternall <hi>Ioue,</hi> rayne ſhowers of vengeance on me,</l>
               <l>plague me for this blacke deed of wrongful hate,</l>
               <l>Be blind mine eyes, they ſhall not looke vpon thee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diego,</hi> till thou be compaſsionate:</l>
               <l>And when thou dooſt forgiue what I haue done,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall they ſhine like ſhorteſt-ſhaded ſunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:41"/>
               <l>O ſlacke thy ſwift-pac'd gallop winged Tyme,</l>
               <l>turne backe, and regiſter this my diſdaine;</l>
               <l>Bid Poets ſing my hate in ruthfull ryme,</l>
               <l>and pen ſad Iliads of <hi>Diegoes</hi> paine:</l>
               <l>Let them be writ in plain-ſeene lines of glaſſe,</l>
               <l>To ſhew how louing he, I, cruell was.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hereat ſhee pauſd, tell me ſweet ſir quoth ſhee,</l>
               <l>how I might ſee my deere-emboſom'd friend,</l>
               <l>That now (if what is paſt may pardned be)</l>
               <l>vnto his griefes I may impoſe an end;</l>
               <l>Where-with they both agreed, that the next day.</l>
               <l>They would eniourney them without more ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long were they not, Deſire ſtill goes on Ice,</l>
               <l>and nere can ſtay tell that he hath his wiſh,</l>
               <l>Mens willing mindes each thing doth ſoone intice,</l>
               <l>to haſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they would faine accompliſh.</l>
               <l>But that they came (as hauing a good guide)</l>
               <l>Vnto the place where they <hi>Diego</hi> ſpide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sacred <hi>Pymplaides</hi> on dip my quill</l>
               <l>within the holy waters of your ſpring,</l>
               <l>Infuze into my braine ſome of your skill,</l>
               <l>that ioyfully of theſe I now may ſing:</l>
               <l>Thoſe Louers now twixt whom late dwelt annoy,</l>
               <l>Swymming in ſeas of ouer-whelming ioy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:41"/>
               <l>But, pardon mee you Dames of Helycon,</l>
               <l>for thus inuoking your diuineſt ayde,</l>
               <l>Which was by me (vnworthy) call'd vpon,</l>
               <l>at your rare knowledge I am much diſmaide;</l>
               <l>My barren-witted braines are all too baſe,</l>
               <l>To be your ſacred learnings reſting place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus, of themſelues, in pleaſures extaſie,</l>
               <l>theſe Louers now embrace them in theyr armes,</l>
               <l>Speechleſſe they are, eye counterſixt on eye,</l>
               <l>like two that are coniur'd by magique charmes,</l>
               <l>So cloſe their armes were twin'd, ſo neer they came</l>
               <l>As if both man and woman were one frame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In th'end, (as doth a Current lately ſtayd,</l>
               <l>ruſh mainly forth his long-impriſoned flood)</l>
               <l>So brake out words; and thus <hi>Dyego</hi> ſayd,</l>
               <l>what my <hi>Gyneura?</hi> O my harts chiefe good,</l>
               <l>Iſt poſſible that thou thy ſelfe ſhould'ſt daigne</l>
               <l>In ſeeing me to take ſo wondrous paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh, ſpeake not of my paine (my deereſt loue)</l>
               <l>all paine is pleaſure that I take for thee,</l>
               <l>Thou that ſo loyall and ſo true dooſt proue,</l>
               <l>might ſcorne mee now, ſo credulous to be:</l>
               <l>Then ſweet <hi>Diego,</hi> let vs now returne,</l>
               <l>And baniſh all things that might make vs mourne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:42"/>
               <l>Twere infinite to tell of their great gladnes,</l>
               <l>theyr amorous greetings, &amp; their ſoules delight,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diego</hi> now had exil'd griefe and ſadnes,</l>
               <l>rauiſht with ioy whilſt he enioyde her ſight.</l>
               <l>Let it ſuffiſe, they homeward now retire,</l>
               <l>Which ſuddaine chance both men &amp; maids admire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gyneura</hi> now delights but in his preſence,</l>
               <l>ſhee cannot once endure him from her ſight,</l>
               <l>His loue-ful face is now her ſoules ſole eſſence,</l>
               <l>and on his face ſhee dotes both day and night.</l>
               <l>She nere did once diſdaine him halfe ſo much,</l>
               <l>As now ſhe honors him, loues force is ſuch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diego</hi> now wrapt in a world of pleaſure,</l>
               <l>imparadiz'd in hauing his deſire,</l>
               <l>Floting in Seas of ioy aboue all meaſure,</l>
               <l>ſought means to mittigate loues burning fire,</l>
               <l>VVho walking with his loue alone one day,</l>
               <l>Diſcharg'd his minde, and thus began to ſay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O faire <hi>Gyneura,</hi> how long wil't be</l>
               <l>ere ſafron-robed <hi>Hymen</hi> doe vnite vs?</l>
               <l>My ſoule doth long that happy howre to ſee.</l>
               <l>O let the angry Fates no longer ſpight vs,</l>
               <l>Lingring delays will teare my greeued hart,</l>
               <l>Let me no longer feele ſo painefull ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:42"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gyneura,</hi> which deſir'd it as her life,</l>
               <l>tells him that paine ſhall ſhortly haue a cure,</l>
               <l>Shortly quoth ſhe, Ile be thy married wife,</l>
               <l>ty'de in thoſe chaynes which euer wil endure,</l>
               <l>Be patient then, and thou ſhalt plainly ſee,</l>
               <l>In working it, how forward I will be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo ſhe was; no time dyd ſhe miſpend,</l>
               <l>wherein ſhee gets not things in readines,</l>
               <l>That might to <hi>Hymens</hi> rites full fitly tend,</l>
               <l>or once conduce to ſuch theyr happines,</l>
               <l>All things prepar'd, theſe Louers now are chayned</l>
               <l>In marriage bands, in which they long remained.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe, whilſt they liu'd, did liue in all content,</l>
               <l>contending who ſhould loue each other moſt,</l>
               <l>To w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure loue, proude Fame her eares down lent,</l>
               <l>and through the world, of it doth highly boaſt.</l>
               <l>O happy he to whom loue comes at laſt,</l>
               <l>That will reſtore what hate before did waſt.</l>
               <l>Then (deereſt loue) <hi>GyneuryZe</hi> at the laſt,</l>
               <l>And I ſhall ſoone forget what ere is paſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>AND now farewel, when I ſhal fare but ill,</l>
               <l>flouriſh &amp; ioy, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhal droope and languiſh,</l>
               <l>All plentious good awaite vpon thy will,</l>
               <l>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> extreame want ſhal bring my ſoule deaths anguiſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10293:43"/>
               <l>Forced by thee (thou mercy-wanting mayd)</l>
               <l>muſt I abandon this my native ſoyle,</l>
               <l>Hoping my ſorrowes heate will be allayd</l>
               <l>by abſence, tyme, neceſſity or toyle.</l>
               <l>So, nowe adiew; the winds call my depart.</l>
               <l>Thy beauties excellence, my rudeſt quill</l>
               <l>Shall neuer-more vnto the world impart,</l>
               <l>ſo that it know thy hate, I haue my will;</l>
               <l>And when thou hear'ſt that I for thee ſhall perriſh,</l>
               <l>Be ſorrowfull. And henceforth true loue cherriſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Poco ſenno basta a chi Fortuna ſuona.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:10293:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
